<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<review>
  <metadata>
    <file>neo-commons/src/neo_commons/platform/actions/application/protocols/action_dispatcher.py</file>
    <language>Py</language>
    <loc>222</loc>
    <reviewer>AI-Claude</reviewer>
    <date>2025-08-30</date>
    <status>complete</status>
  </metadata>

  <scores>
    <metric name="security" score="4" open_issues="1"/>
    <metric name="performance" score="5" open_issues="0"/>
    <metric name="maintainability" score="4" open_issues="1"/>
    <metric name="consistency" score="2" open_issues="2"/>
    <metric name="best_practices" score="2" open_issues="2"/>
    <metric name="code_smell" score="3" open_issues="1"/>
  </scores>

  <issues>
    <issue category="security" severity="LOW">
      <title>Schema Parameter Validation Missing</title>
      <location>Lines 20, 38, 57, 75, 85, 98, 118, 137, 154, 172, 189, 209</location>
      <description>Schema parameters are directly passed to database operations without validation, creating potential SQL injection risk if schema names contain special characters</description>
      <recommendation>Add schema parameter validation to ensure only valid schema names are accepted, or use a whitelist of allowed schemas</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="maintainability" severity="MEDIUM">
      <title>Large Protocol Interface</title>
      <location>Entire file</location>
      <description>The protocol defines 12 methods, violating single responsibility principle and making it difficult to implement and maintain</description>
      <recommendation>Split into separate protocols: ActionDispatcher, ExecutionScheduler, ExecutionMonitor based on functional concerns</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="consistency" severity="HIGH">
      <title>ABC Pattern Used Instead of @runtime_checkable Protocol</title>
      <location>Lines 3, 13</location>
      <description>Uses ABC inheritance pattern instead of @runtime_checkable Protocol, inconsistent with neo-commons dependency injection patterns</description>
      <recommendation>Convert to @runtime_checkable Protocol pattern for consistency with other neo-commons protocols</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="consistency" severity="MEDIUM">
      <title>Mixed Sync/Async Method Return Types</title>
      <location>Lines 137, 155</location>
      <description>Methods like cancel_execution() return bool while get_execution_status() returns Optional[Dict[str, Any]], creating inconsistent return type patterns</description>
      <recommendation>Standardize return types using consistent result objects or optional patterns across all methods</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="best_practices" severity="HIGH">
      <title>Missing Exception Documentation</title>
      <location>All method docstrings</location>
      <description>Protocol methods don't document expected exceptions, making it difficult for implementations to handle errors consistently</description>
      <recommendation>Add 'Raises:' section to all method docstrings specifying expected exception types</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="best_practices" severity="MEDIUM">
      <title>Generic Return Types</title>
      <location>Lines 155, 211</location>
      <description>Methods return generic Dict[str, Any] instead of typed response objects, reducing type safety and API clarity</description>
      <recommendation>Define specific response dataclasses for status information and monitoring reports</recommendation>
    </issue>
    
    <issue category="code_smell" severity="MEDIUM">
      <title>Multiple Responsibilities in Single Protocol</title>
      <location>Entire file</location>
      <description>Protocol handles event dispatching, action execution, scheduling, retries, monitoring, and queue processing - too many concerns</description>
      <recommendation>Extract separate protocols: IActionMatcher, IActionExecutor, IExecutionScheduler, IExecutionMonitor</recommendation>
    </issue>
  </issues>

  <summary>Protocol interface for action dispatcher handling event routing to actions. Defines comprehensive interface with 12 methods covering dispatching, execution, scheduling, retries, and monitoring. Uses ABC pattern instead of @runtime_checkable Protocol pattern. Contains multiple responsibilities that should be separated.</summary>

  <positive_observations>
    <observation>Comprehensive docstrings with clear parameter descriptions and return value explanations</observation>
    <observation>Good separation between event dispatching and action execution concerns in method signatures</observation>
    <observation>Proper async/await patterns throughout all method definitions</observation>
    <observation>Consistent parameter naming conventions (schema, event, action) across all methods</observation>
    <observation>Sensible default values for optional parameters like parallel=True and limit=100</observation>
    <observation>Good type hints using proper generic types and imports from typing module</observation>
  </positive_observations>

  <context>
    <tests>No test files found for this protocol interface</tests>
    <documentation>Comprehensive docstrings with parameter descriptions and return types, but missing exception documentation</documentation>
    <configuration>Protocol interface - no configuration required</configuration>
  </context>

  <checklist>
    <item completed="true">Lints clean</item>
    <item completed="false">Tests present</item>
    <item completed="true">Documentation updated</item>
    <item completed="true">Security review complete</item>
    <item completed="true">Performance acceptable</item>
  </checklist>
</review>